<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Panthea: or, Diuine vvishes and meditations: vvritten by Io. Siluester: reuised by I.M. Master of Arts. Whereunto is added an appendix, containing an excellent elegy, written by the L. Viscount St. Albans, late Lord High Chancelour of England. &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Sylvester, Josuah, 1563-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853283</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853283</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18654</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13277)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18654)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1157:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Panthea: or, Diuine vvishes and meditations: vvritten by Io. Siluester: reuised by I.M. Master of Arts. Whereunto is added an appendix, containing an excellent elegy, written by the L. Viscount St. Albans, late Lord High Chancelour of England. &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Sylvester, Josuah, 1563-1618.</author>
                  <author>Martin, James, fl. 1615-1630.</author>
                  <author>Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by George Purslowe] for F. Coules, and are to be sold at his shop in the vpper end of the Old-Baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Editor's dedication signed: Iames Martin.</note>
                  <note>L. Viscount St. Albans = Francis Bacon.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>"Appendix to Panthea" has separate dated title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:1"/>
                  <p>PANTHEA: OR, DIVINE VVISHES AND MEDITATIONS: Written by <hi>Io. Siluester:</hi> Reuiſed by <hi>I.M.</hi> Maſter of Arts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fero &amp; ſpero.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereunto is added an <hi>Appendix,</hi> containing an Excellent Elegy, written by the L. Viſcount S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Albans,</hi> late Lord High Chancelour of <hi>England. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>person by tree</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>F. Coules,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in the vpper end of the Old-Baily. 1630.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:2"/>
                  <head>To the very Honorable Knight, and <hi>Magnificent Baronet,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> RICHARD HOVGHTON of <hi>Houghton-Tower:</hi> All Health, Honor, and Happineſſe.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Honor'd Sir:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He heauenly Light of Diuine Truth ſhining in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, hath enabled our Soules cleerely to ſee their owne Excellence; <hi>viz.</hi> that they are by Creation <hi>Spirits</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Eccles. 12.7.</note> or ſpirituall Subſtances; of an
<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 10.28.</note> immortall Nature; in Duration, eternall; as being (in <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> phraſe) <hi>Afflatus oris Diuini,</hi> the immediate Handiworke of God; and conſequently
<note n="c" place="margin">Quicquid ex nihilo fit, eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptibile.</note> incorruptible. Yea, ſuch is their exquiſite Beauty and abſolute Perfection (conſidered in their owne
<note n="d" place="margin">The Eſſence of God, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, &amp; Soules, is knowne to God alone ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly. <hi>Athanaſ. Tract. de Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiombus.</hi>
                     </note> Eſſence) as the moſt amiable Reflex of <hi>Diamonds,</hi> the Virgin-bluſhes of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies,</hi> the azure veines of <hi>Saphires,</hi> the greene luſtre of <hi>Emeralds,</hi> the various beames of <hi>Iacincts,</hi> and the radiant conſtellations of the faireſt and moſt Orient <hi>Vnions,</hi> are neuer able to parallell. Thus Nobly-deſcended and rarely-qualified is the Soule; a Creature of ſuch An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Serenity, as that the <hi>MAIESTY</hi> of <hi>HEAVEN (enamour'd</hi> on his owne bright Image) made this goodly Globe of Heauen
<note n="e" place="margin">Ita S. Chryſoſt.</note> and Earh for her ſolace and Contemplation, <hi>wooed</hi> her with moſt ardent and inflam'd Affection, ſtiling her
<note n="f" place="margin">In <hi>Salomons</hi> Song.</note> 
                     <hi>his Loue, his Doue, his Siſter, his Spouſe:</hi> and laſtly, <hi>married</hi> her to Himſelfe for euer, by aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming our <hi>Humane
<note n="g" place="margin">Deus &amp; huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na natura vniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: non Deus &amp; Homo; quia non Perſona &amp; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona. Aſſumpſit Deus non Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſed Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem.</note> Nature,</hi> which hauing hypoſtatically and indiſſolubly vnited to his DEITY, hee accompliſht in it the moſt Admirable Worke of our Redemption, inueſted it with Jm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality by his Reſurrection, and aduanced it to his Heauenly Kingdome (far aboue all Coeleſtiall Powers) by his Aſcenſion. And now is MAN, in regard of this ſuperexcellent Honour, become (in this point) ſuperiour to the ANGELS, as being participant of the
<pb facs="tcp:18654:3"/>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pet. Ep. 2. chap. 1. v. 4.</note> Diuine Nature ſubſiſting in the moſt Sacred Perſon of our euer-bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord JESVS, whoſe glorified Humanity is moſt triumphantly enthroniz'd at the Right Hand of God on High.</p>
                  <p>Thus hath the King of Angels (in his ineffable loue to our Soules) exalted this humane Fleſh, aboue the higheſt Hierarchy; to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement of thoſe Heauenly Spirits, (as the
<note n="i" place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pet. Ep. 1. chap. 1. v. 12.</note> Prince of th' Apoſtles intimateth.) Neuertheleſſe, if an exact Suruey be taken of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World, will there not be found in all Eſtates ſuch a generall Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie from the Loue of God, as if Men were altogether Soule-leſse; or (at leaſt) Senſe-leſſe how infinitely the Creator of the World values that peereleſſe Pearle, which this ſhell of Mortality containes: [a Pearle ſo ineſtimable, as nothing in Heauen or Earth, but the very
<note n="k" place="margin">Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Heart was pierced with the ſpeare for our ſinnes: O that our hearts might be pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with true compunction and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance! other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wee haue no part in his Paſsion.</note> 
                     <hi>HEART BLOOD</hi> of the <hi>ONELY SONNE</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi> could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme] To inſtance this ſottiſh Madneſſe, and Epidemicall Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in all Degrees and Delinquents, were infinite J will therfore (in preſent) cull out onely ſome, that are (in their owne Conceits) the Creame of Chriſtendoms, the pureſt and demureſt <hi>Profeſſants,</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of whom the obedient Children of the Church of England, are reputed prophane and Vnſanctified Perſons.
<note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccl. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Euſebius</hi> (an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticke and approued Author) hath a memorable H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtorie applia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to this purpoſe. He relates how he ſaw at <hi>Tyre</hi> (a City of <hi>Phoeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi>) diuers naked Chriſtians expoſed by their Perſecutors to cruell Panthers, mighty Beares, and
<note n="m" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> wild Bores, to be deuoured by them: which rauenous Beaſts, although they were prouoked by the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to aſsaile them, (for ſo were the poore Soules commanded) yet they vtterly refuſed to hurt or approach them: but on the contrary, they ſlew at the Inſidels (without the Barres) which exaſperated them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chriſtians. To make ſome Application and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of this rare and miraculous Euent: I haue learned by good Intelligence, and your Noble Selfe, with many Thouſands (in <hi>plagâ hyper-Boreâ</hi>) were ocular Witneſſes, that certaine externall Profeſſors
<note n="n" place="margin">Of theſe, ſee an excellent Sermon, called <hi>Corona Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> pag. 28, 29, 30.</note> of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, yet internall Contemners of the Ordinance of Chriſt in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of their <hi>owne
<note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> Paſtors,</hi> hauing long panted after their <hi>Extirpation</hi> and Deſtruction, combin'd together at laſt (as cloſe as
<note n="p" place="margin">See Iob c. 41. v. 15, 16, 17.</note> 
                     <hi>Leuiathans</hi> ſoules) to <hi>ſtrip</hi> them of their Reuenues, incarcerate
<note n="q" place="margin">A Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Act. Reu. 2.10. Thus the <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> raged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Teachers, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> who was faine to ſlye from their helliſh ſurie. See his Apologie for his Flight, &amp;c. and his Epiſtle <hi>ad Solitarios:</hi> where he writes, that hauing beene twice depriued by 2 falſe Synods, he was at laſt abſolued, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to his Church, notwithſtanding the former Sentences of the Hereticall Biſhops, who (as he elegantly termes them) were rather <hi>Cataſcopi</hi> then <hi>Epiſcopi,</hi> Catchpoles then Biſhops.</note> their Perſons, diſſeaze them of their Frecholds, (by Bribery and
<pb facs="tcp:18654:3"/>Legall Sleights) diſsipate their Goods, ruinate their Families, begger their Poſterities, and (to teare them quite in pieces; O moſt deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Immanity!) infame them with a thouſand virulent Asperſions and venemous Jmputations: aſſuring themſelues, though their tongues ranne neuer ſo falſe a Gallop, yet ſome <hi>maleficiate</hi> or other would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them: [the credulity of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar (eſpecially in Clorgie mens Caſes) being ſuch, <hi>as if a Gnat but ſpread his Wings betweene them and the Sunne, to thinke it eclipſed.</hi>] Theſe things being ſo, let any Chriſtian or Pagan iudge, whether thoſe wild beaſts in <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> were not infinitely more humane, compaſsionate, and mercifull to the deſigned Martyrs; then were theſe vnchriſtian Kernes, masked Miſcreants, and Diabolicall <hi>Decoy's,</hi> to their <hi>conformable</hi> Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers; in whoſe Coats ſeeing they could not <hi>finde</hi> a hole, they reſolued to <hi>fret</hi> one. Vndoubtedly (you bloody Bores, ſelfe-admiring Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines and Cyclopicall Canibals) your crying Sinnes and thundering Crimes of Oppreſsion and Ravine (though mantled with Hypocriſie, the Deuils Masking-ſute) haue entred the
<note n="r" place="margin">Iam. 5.4.</note> eares of the Lord of Hoſts. For howeuer this vnhallowed Crew may (in a ſpirituall Phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy) flatter and hug themſelues in their abhorred Rapacity, and ſing <hi>Requiems</hi> and <hi>Lullabies</hi> to their ſenſeleſſe Soules, and cauterized Conſciences, as if they ſhould neuer tremble before the terrible Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of the Iudge of all the World, for theſe blacke Deeds, and execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Enormities: yet certainely theſe <hi>artificiall Villanies</hi> are <hi>Vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra in capite canis,</hi> ſuch mortall Wounds to their <hi>inward-bleeding</hi> Soules, as thoſe <hi>Saluages</hi> ſhall neuer <hi>licke whole</hi> with a generall and ſuperficiall Confeſsion of their ſinnes, nor be once admitted to Gods ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<note n="ſ" place="margin">Obſerue well what our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaith tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this point, Matth. 5. v. 23, 24.</note> Altar, to make their peace with him, till they be firſt reconciled to their offended Brother, and haue (to their vtmoſt Ability) made due Repaire of Honour, and Reſtitution of Liuelyhood to the Parties ſo hamouſly wronged. And albeit this <hi>Canting Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity</hi> ſeeme to haue made a League with Satan, and are yet inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Horrour <hi>of the Fact:</hi> notwithſtanding, as that which is written with the juice of a LIMON, apreares not at firſt, till you hold it to the Fire: So, when theſe diſ-gallanted
<note n="t" place="margin">See Act. 14, from the 11. v. to the 20.</note> 
                     <hi>Lycaonians</hi> ſhal one day, (without ſpeedy and effectuall Repentance) haue the full Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls of Gods <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>engeance powred and <hi>preſt on</hi> them, (roaring in Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire with
<note n="u" place="margin">In an old Manuſcript lately found at <hi>Cheſter,</hi> it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, that <hi>Pilate</hi> was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pontius, à Ponte,</hi> of a Bridge; and not of the Ile <hi>Pontas:</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, he is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally held a damned miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creant.</note> 
                     <hi>PONTIVS Pilate, Barabbas,</hi> and other Infernall Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) then ſhall they cleerely reade in the blacke Bookes of their vaſt Conſciences, their Barbarous Acts, and Deuiliſh Complots, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the hugeſt <hi>Capitals.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:4"/>
                  <p>But to returne where WE BEGAN, and to leaue theſe merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Wretches to the Judgement of God; whom (from the Center of my Soule) I beſeech to giue them the Grace of
<note n="x" place="margin">The proper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ct of Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nce (in this Caſe) is Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ution or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>efaction; without which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aileth the Delinquent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hough he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hould hang <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>imſelfe with <hi>Judas.</hi>
                     </note> Repentance: J haue here (Moſt Honor'd Sir) preſum'd (in lieu of your many ſignall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours) to preſent you this ſmall Manual of Meditations in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe, publiſhed vnder the Coniunction and ſweet Aſpect of moſt eminent STARS, and written (as I am credibly certified) by a Diuine Laureat (deceaſed;) whoſe maine Drift is to eleuate the Soule to Heauen, from theſe bewitching Vanities of the
<note n="y" place="margin">The Earth was made for Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Man for Earth.</note> Earth: A Noble and Coeleſtiall Theme, and neuer more ſeaſonable then now: In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, I was confident it would be no vnwelcome Newyeeres-gift to your Noble-ſpirited Selfe, whoſe Heroicke Dispoſition and pious Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to Diuine Exerciſes, and Compoſures, accompanied with a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall Hand to learned and Orthodox Eccleſiaſticks, and a piercing Iudgement wiſely to diſcerne betwixt an accompliſht Scholler, and a popular <hi>Parakito,</hi> or <hi>Skip-Iacke</hi>-Fellow of empty Boldneſse; as alſo your frequent Largeſſes to the Peore, and Donatiues to the Diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; your graue Moderation and prudent Diſpenſation of Iuſtice; your generous Hoſpitaelity, rare Affability, and vnexampled Humanity; your reſplendent Dignity, Illuſtrious Family, and Honourable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, haue purchas'd you the ſingular Loue and Obſeruance of all good Patriots. Your Magnifique Entertainement of his late
<note n="z" place="margin">King <hi>Iames:</hi> (In his Return from <hi>Scotland.</hi>)</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie (of Sacred Memory) at your Baſilicall TOWER, [one of the braueſt Seates in <hi>Europe</hi>] was no ſmall Renowne to your Selfe, and your moſt Nobly-accompliſht
<note n="a" place="margin">Sir <hi>Gilbert Honghton.</hi>
                     </note> Sonne: But your Munificence to the oppreſſed and afflicted members of Ieſus Chriſt, [ſeaſoned with true Faith and
<note n="b" place="margin">Contritio eſt extremitas do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loris.</note> Contrition; and ſugred with Holineſſe, <hi>without
<note n="d" place="margin">Reu. 2.10.</note> which, no man ſhall ſee the Lord</hi>] will gaine you (at laſt) <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Amarantinam,</hi> an Imperiall Diadem
<note n="c" place="margin">Hebrewes, chap. 12, v. 14.</note> of Bliſſe (with your peere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Lady deceaſed) in the Empyréall Heauen. Thrice Happy, O! and moſt Heauenly Soules, whom the bleſſed Angels ſhall ſo beare in Triumph to that Glorious Ieruſalem! To which Soueraigne Felicity, that your euer-honor'd Selfe, your Worthy Sonnes, and Excellent Daughters (the Cryſtall Mirrors of Modeſty) may arriue (at the end of this Span-long Life;) is the hearty Prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Auguſtae Trinobantum. <date>Feſto Theogonias.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your Noble Vertues moſt affectionate Obſeruer, IAMES MARTIN, One of his late Maieſties Preachers, and Commiſſioners Eccleſiaſticall in the Prouince of <hi>Yorke.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:4"/>
                  <head>To the moſt reſplendent Diamonds of the North, and ſingular Glories of their Sex:
<list>
                        <item>The Lady IVLIANA WALMIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEY, Siſter to the Right Honorable and Excellent Peere, RICHARD Lord MOLINEVX Viſcount <hi>Marbrugh:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Miſtris <hi>Mary Walmiſſey,</hi> Siſter to the Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icke Knight and Baronet, Sir <hi>Richard Houghton</hi> of <hi>Houghton</hi>-Tower.</item>
                        <item>Miſtris <hi>Grace Houghton,</hi> Wife to the thrice-Worthy Gentleman, <hi>William Houghton</hi> Eſquire; and Daughter to the euer-renowned Knight, Sir <hi>Richard Sherborne</hi> of <hi>Stonihurſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Lady ANNE OSBORNE and Miſtris <hi>Elizabeth Sherborne,</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the perfect-Honorable Gent. <hi>Tho. Walmiſley</hi> Eſquire, and Neeces to the moſt Illuſtrious Lord, HENRY Earle of <hi>Danby.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Miſtris <hi>Frances Houghton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Miſtris <hi>Gillebert Houghton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Miſtris <hi>Anne Houghton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Miſtris <hi>Katherine Houghton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Miſtris <hi>Margaret Anderton,</hi> Neece to the Generous and Iudicious Gentleman, <hi>Roger Bradſhagh</hi> of <hi>Hagh,</hi> Eſquire.</item>
                     </list>
I. M. <hi>the Publiſher of theſe Soliloquies, conſecrates them, deuotes himſelfe, wiſhes all imaginable Happineſſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>LADIE IVLIANA WALMISLEY, <hi>Her Anagram.</hi> I am a Lilly; <hi>Diana's</hi> Iewell.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>LOoke as the LILLY doth each Flower excell,</l>
                        <l>In <hi>Milke-white</hi> Luſtre, and in <hi>Purple</hi> Dy:</l>
                        <l>So in your Heauenly Face, combined dwell</l>
                        <l>Pure ſpotleſſe <hi>Candor,</hi> Roſeat <hi>Modeſty:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Fame, take thy Golden Trumpe, and her proclaime,</l>
                        <l>DIANA'S IEVVELL; Glory of her Name.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18654:5"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18654:5"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18654:6"/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>To the ſame Noble HEROINES.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>WIt's, Honor's, Beautie's Angelized Frames,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Vertue's faire Temples, Wonders of your Names,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which gild</hi> that Climate <hi>with your Glorious Beames,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Beyond the Luſtre of Starres twinckling gleames;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Crowne with your Fauors theſe Diuiner Laies,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which tune your Soules to ſound your Makers Praiſe:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>So may you ſhine more bright in true renowne,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Than Golden Starres in</hi> Ariadne's <hi>Crowne.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>I. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <hi>A Muzzle for</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Hylax in limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne latrat.</note> Momus.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>IF any (like the</hi>
                        <note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond great Duke of <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couia,</hi> ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor'd Women, that he ſwoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſight of them. <hi>Bodin, de Repub.</hi>
                        </note> Moſcouiticke <hi>Duke</hi>)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reſſent</hi> the other Sex, <hi>and their iuſt Praiſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whoſe Natiue Splendor needs no other Raies;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May no ſuch</hi> Baſiliske <hi>dart vpon this Booke</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His poiſonous Eies: ſuch</hi>
                        <note n="c" place="margin">A moſt viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Sycopha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. See <hi>Ariſtophan. Equites:</hi> and <hi>Thucydides,</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 4.) exquiſitly rendered by that Worthy learned Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>The. Hobs,</hi> Secretary to the late Excellent Earle of <hi>Deuon.</hi>
                        </note> Cleon's <hi>ſilenc'd beſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By Noble Scorne. So ſet I vp my reſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I. M.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="panegyric">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:6"/>
                  <head>A Panegyre, To the Author.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>OFt haue I wiſht, (thy <hi>Worth</hi> that <hi>Wiſh</hi> did moue)</l>
                     <l>My Seat neere to the Muſes Bay-tree Groue;</l>
                     <l>Or by that <hi>Spring</hi> for Poeſie moſt admir'd;</l>
                     <l>That being by ſome Sacred Power <hi>inſpir'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I from thoſe Bankes might haue ſelected Flowers</l>
                     <l>Water'd with ſweet <hi>Castaliaes</hi> ſiluer Showres:</l>
                     <l>Then ſhould my Hand thy Brow a <hi>Wreath</hi> haue made;</l>
                     <l>But ſince I ſit not in the <hi>Laurell-ſhade,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I cannot giue what thy Deſerts doe claime;</l>
                     <l>Far ſhort be my Deſires of their high Ayme:</l>
                     <l>So ſtands a <hi>Shepheard</hi> pointing at a <hi>Starre</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>As I at <hi>Thee,</hi> thy Light tranſcending farre:</l>
                     <l>Thou doſt our Thoughts to <hi>Speculation</hi> tye,</l>
                     <l>Like ſome cleere <hi>Fountaine,</hi> where the Cryſtall <hi>Sky</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her bright-vnwrinkled-azure brow may ſee,</l>
                     <l>So doe the Heauens behold their Face in <hi>Thee:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy <hi>Heart,</hi> the <hi>Firmament</hi> of faithfull Truth,</l>
                     <l>Thy <hi>Arts,</hi> the gliſtring <hi>Starres</hi> that grac'd thy Youth:</l>
                     <l>Thy <hi>Soule</hi> the <hi>Cynthia,</hi> whoſe bright-ſhining Raies</l>
                     <l>Lighted the <hi>World</hi> to haue reform'd her Waies:</l>
                     <l>Thy <hi>All,</hi> a Little-World of richer Frame,</l>
                     <l>Then that which did poſſeſſe the <hi>Golden</hi> Name.</l>
                     <l>Hence then, you <hi>Termagants</hi> to
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Ætnae:</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be <hi>Plutoes</hi> Court.</note> 
                        <hi>Mongibell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>You
<note n="*" place="margin">Certaine hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrionicall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, (Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                           <hi>Iohn Lacke-Latine</hi>) in the Vniuerſity of <hi>Fooliana;</hi> which ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodically cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure all Verſes whatſoeuer.</note> 
                        <hi>Pantalouns,</hi> that POESY damne to Hell:</l>
                     <l>Peace yawning Goblins, <hi>Hob, Dick, Hick</hi> and <hi>Will,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Spue not your Gall againſt his <hi>Sacred</hi> Quill:</l>
                     <l>To <hi>ſuch</hi> may euery Leafe, and euery Line</l>
                     <l>An <hi>Armadillo</hi> be, or <hi>Porcupine.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>S. N. <hi>à ſacerrimis Catharis &amp; Lavernio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus horrendiffimè ſpoliatus.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:7"/>
                  <head>The Authors Inuocation and Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation againſt his Infernall Enemies.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SVpreame Commander of the Cryſtall Sky,</l>
                     <l>That ALL of NOTHING powerfully didſt frame,</l>
                     <l>Bee't not offenſe againſt thy Deity,</l>
                     <l>With humble Accents to adore thy Name:</l>
                     <l>Though in this Teare-compoſed Terrene Globe,</l>
                     <l>I weare Mortalities Sin-ſtained Robe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let me behold with Contemplations Eye,</l>
                     <l>The Beauty of thine Angell-guarded Throne:</l>
                     <l>And let my ſoule with humble boldneſſe fly,</l>
                     <l>Aboue the Starry Conſtellation:</l>
                     <l>And there with that moſt holy Hierarchy,</l>
                     <l>Sing Hymnes and Anthems to thy Deity.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let my ſad Soule, long pierc'd with Swords of Griefe</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Fiends, Alastors, Harpyes, Furies</hi> fell,</l>
                     <l>Receiue (my God) from thee Diuine Reliefe,</l>
                     <l>Which may their Pride and canker'd Malice quell:</l>
                     <l>Make thoſe <hi>pure Hell-Dogs</hi> in their Dens to couch,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Belzebub</hi> himſelfe at laſt to crouch.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:7"/>
                  <head>PANTHEA.</head>
                  <div n="induction" type="part">
                     <head>The Induction.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>WHat ſhould I wiſh for on the Earth?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Goodnes <hi>is growne to ſuch a dearth;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>While want of</hi> Grace <hi>doth make abuſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of that which might be for good Vſe:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That who obſerues what most men wiſh,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Shall find how fond and vaine it is.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Some wiſh for</hi> Wealth, <hi>to pamper Pride;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Medicine good, but ill-applide.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Some wiſh for</hi> Honour, <hi>in high thought;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Honour is good, Ambition nought.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Some wiſh for</hi> Health, <hi>to liue at eaſe;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Health may be good, Eaſe breeds Diſeaſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Some wiſh for</hi> Power, <hi>to wrong at will;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Power oft is good, Oppreſsion ill.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Some wiſh for</hi> Youth, <hi>to nouriſh Folly;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Youth may be good, the Wiſh vnholy.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Some wiſh for</hi> Loue, <hi>to anſwer Luſt;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Loue may be good, the Wiſh vnjuſt.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Some wiſh for</hi> Strength <hi>to cruſh and kill,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Strength may be good, but Murther ill.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thus ſtill th' Abuſe which Will brings forth</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Doth make the Wiſhes nothing worth.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yet ſince that</hi> Wiſhes <hi>may be good,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When Worth is truly vnderſtood,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18654:8"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Let me ſet downe my Hearts deſire,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And what hath ſet my Soule on ſire.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>It is not Earth, nor earthly Treaſure,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor worldly Honour, fleſhly Pleaſure,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor Power, nor Place, nor Youth, nor Strength,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor drawing out this Life at length.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor idle pleaſing Natures Eye</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With fond Affections Vanity.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Not one of theſe comes neere the</hi> White</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of my Hearts Wiſh and Soules Delight.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Courſe of my true Cares content</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Extends aboue the Firmament.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The lenell of my Soules chiefe Loue</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Is onely in the Heauens aboue;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Where I ſhall ſee my Sauiour ſweet,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And how his Saints and Augels meet</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With ſuch an Harmony of voyces,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>As ſhewes how euery Soule reioyces</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In the beholding his ſweet Face,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That is the Glory of all Grace.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This, this, my</hi> Wiſh <hi>ſhall onely be,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To liue where I may euer ſee</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>My Sauiour ſweet, and in his ſight</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Haue all my Hearts and Soules Delight.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Daigne then (my God) this</hi> Boone <hi>to giue</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Whiles here vpon this Earth I liue,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That neither</hi> Wealth, <hi>nor</hi> Pouerty,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor</hi> Comfort, <hi>nor</hi> Calamity,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor</hi> Health, <hi>nor</hi> Sicknes; Eaſe <hi>nor</hi> Paine,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor</hi> Hope, <hi>nor</hi> Feare; <hi>nor</hi> Loſſe, <hi>nor</hi> Gaine,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>May euer take ſuch hold on me,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But ſtill my Ioy in</hi> CHRIST <hi>may be.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="wish">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18654:8"/>
                     <head>I. <hi>Wiſh,</hi> or <hi>Meditation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OH! had <hi>I</hi> of his <hi>Loue</hi> but part,</l>
                        <l>That choſen was by Gods own heart,</l>
                        <l>That Princely Prophet, DAVID, he</l>
                        <l>Whom in the Word of Truth I ſee</l>
                        <l>The King of Heauen ſo dearely lou'd,</l>
                        <l>As Mercy beyond meaſure prou'd:</l>
                        <l>Then ſhould I neither <hi>Gyant</hi> feare,</l>
                        <l>Nor <hi>Lion,</hi> that my Soule would teare;</l>
                        <l>Nor the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> nor ſuch Fiends</l>
                        <l>As neuer were true Chriſtians friends:</l>
                        <l>No <hi>Paſsion</hi> ſhould my Spirit vex,</l>
                        <l>Nor <hi>Sorrow</hi> ſo my minde perplex,</l>
                        <l>But I ſhould ſtill all Glory giue</l>
                        <l>Unto my God by whom I liue.</l>
                        <l>Then <hi>Health,</hi> nor <hi>Sickneſſe, Griefe,</hi> nor <hi>Eaſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Should ſo my mind diſeaſe or pleaſe,</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Want,</hi> or <hi>We,</hi> what-ere I proue,</l>
                        <l>The Lord of Life ſhould be my Loue.</l>
                        <l>To him I ſhould my mind impart,</l>
                        <l>And to him onely giue my heart,</l>
                        <l>And to his mercy onely pray,</l>
                        <l>To put my ſecret ſinnes away:</l>
                        <l>To heale my ſinfull wounded Soule,</l>
                        <l>And put my Name in Mercies Roll:</l>
                        <l>In all my <hi>Cares</hi> and <hi>Croſſes</hi> ſtill</l>
                        <l>To comfort me with his good Will:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18654:9"/>
                        <l>And when I cry and rore in Griefe,</l>
                        <l>In deepe deſpaire of Hopes Reliefe,</l>
                        <l>My Faith ſhould yet in Mercy finde</l>
                        <l>The Comfort of a conſtant Minde,</l>
                        <l>And I ſhould euer ioy to ſee</l>
                        <l>How Mercies Eye did looke on mee:</l>
                        <l>Then ſhould my Heart tune euery ſtring,</l>
                        <l>That to his glory I might ſing</l>
                        <l>A <hi>Song</hi> of euer-laſting Praiſe,</l>
                        <l>To end in neuer-ending daies.</l>
                        <l>Then ſhould I <hi>play,</hi> and <hi>ſing,</hi> and <hi>dance,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And to the Heauens mine Eyes aduance,</l>
                        <l>With ioy to ſee in Triumph ſo</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Arke</hi> of God in Glory go:</l>
                        <l>And whatſoeuer I poſſeſſe</l>
                        <l>In <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Honour,</hi> more or leſſe,</l>
                        <l>Nor Earth nor Heauen ſhould me moue,</l>
                        <l>But ſtill my Lord ſhould be my Loue.</l>
                        <l>If I were <hi>ſicke;</hi> He were my <hi>Health;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>If I were <hi>poore;</hi> He were my <hi>Wealth;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>If I were <hi>weake;</hi> He were my <hi>Strength;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>If <hi>dead;</hi> He were my <hi>Life,</hi> at length.</l>
                        <l>If <hi>ſcorn'd;</hi> He onely were my <hi>Grace:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>If <hi>baniſht;</hi> He my <hi>Reſting-place.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>If <hi>wrong'd;</hi> He onely were my <hi>Right:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>If <hi>ſad;</hi> He were my Soules <hi>Delight.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>In ſumme, and all, All-onely He</l>
                        <l>Should be All, aboue All, to me.</l>
                        <l>His <hi>Hand</hi> ſhould wipe away my <hi>Teares,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>His <hi>Fauor</hi> free me from all <hi>Feares,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>His <hi>Mercy</hi> pardon all my <hi>Sinne,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>His <hi>Grace</hi> my life <hi>anew</hi> begin;</l>
                        <l>His <hi>Loue</hi> my <hi>Light</hi> to Heauen ſhould bee,</l>
                        <l>His <hi>Glory,</hi> thus to <hi>comfort</hi> me.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18654:9"/>
                        <l>Thus was this Kingly Prophet bleſt,</l>
                        <l>To liue in Loues eternall Reſt.</l>
                        <l>And ſince I ſee his Grace ſo great,</l>
                        <l>To all that Mercy doe intreat,</l>
                        <l>And how the faithfull Soule doth proue</l>
                        <l>An heauenly Bleſſing in his Loue;</l>
                        <l>Let me but onely <hi>This</hi> requeſt,</l>
                        <l>To be but <hi>thus</hi> with <hi>Dauid</hi> bleſt,</l>
                        <l>That <hi>Ioy,</hi> or <hi>Griefe,</hi> what-e're I proue,</l>
                        <l>The Lord of Life may be my Loue.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="wish">
                     <head>II. <hi>Wiſh, or Meditation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OH that I were as <hi>Wiſe</hi> as
<note n="*" place="margin">Salomon,</note> He</l>
                        <l>That did by Obſeruation ſee</l>
                        <l>What All things are, with all their Worth,</l>
                        <l>That vnder Heauen the Earth brings forth,</l>
                        <l>How <hi>vaine</hi> they are, and how they vex</l>
                        <l>The Soule whom <hi>Paſsion</hi> doth perplex.</l>
                        <l>Then ſhould I neither <hi>carke</hi> nor <hi>care</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>For things that ſo vncertaine are;</l>
                        <l>Nor toyle nor labour for a Life</l>
                        <l>So full of Falſhood, Feare, and ſtrife.</l>
                        <l>Nor ayme at Title, Power, or Place,</l>
                        <l>Nor Fauour, Wealth, or Worldly Grace;</l>
                        <l>Nor trouble Patience with a hope</l>
                        <l>Of ought beyond my onely Scope:</l>
                        <l>Nor ſooth, nor flatter, lye, nor ſweare,</l>
                        <l>Nor ſtand in Danger, nor in Feare</l>
                        <l>Of him, of her; of this, of that,</l>
                        <l>Nor hunt I know not after what:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18654:10"/>
                        <l>But loue the Meaſure and the Meane,</l>
                        <l>That keepes the Soule and Body cleane.</l>
                        <l>Then ſhould I finde this Life, but Breath</l>
                        <l>That Sinne hath ſubiect made to Death:</l>
                        <l>For from the greateſt to the leaſt,</l>
                        <l>No Soule but liues at ſome vnreſt:</l>
                        <l>The ſoundeſt and the deepeſt <hi>Wit</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Sometimes in idle Thoughts doth ſit;</l>
                        <l>The faireſt and the ſweeteſt <hi>Face</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Is ſometime ſubiect to Diſgrace.</l>
                        <l>The Nobleſt and the valiant'ſt <hi>Minde,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Sometime may hap goe downe the Winde.</l>
                        <l>The richeſt <hi>Hand,</hi> and proudeſt <hi>Heart,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>May chance to play the Beggers part.</l>
                        <l>The valiant'ſt Arme, and ſtrongeſt Hand,</l>
                        <l>Sometime at <hi>Mercies</hi> Gate may ſtand.</l>
                        <l>The pureſt <hi>Soule</hi> that would not ſinne,</l>
                        <l>May chance to fall in Satans Ginne.</l>
                        <l>Then ſince I ſee there is no ſtate,</l>
                        <l>But that ſometime, or ſoone, or late,</l>
                        <l>Is ſubiect to ſo hard a courſe</l>
                        <l>As leaues the <hi>Better</hi> for the <hi>Worſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Though I be not ſo wiſe as <hi>Hee</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That made me <hi>This</hi> to know and ſee,</l>
                        <l>Yet will I ioyne with him in this,</l>
                        <l>Vpon <hi>this Earth</hi> to build no <hi>Bliſſe;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But with the Wings of <hi>Faith</hi> to flye</l>
                        <l>Vnto my Glorious God on high:</l>
                        <l>And in his <hi>Mercy</hi> only proue</l>
                        <l>The Bleſſings for my <hi>Soules</hi> behoofe;</l>
                        <l>From <hi>Sorrow, Sinne,</hi> and <hi>Satan</hi> free;</l>
                        <l>And loue the <hi>World</hi> that liſt (for me.)</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="wish">
                     <pb facs="tcp:18654:10"/>
                     <head>III. <hi>Wiſh, or Meditation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OH! that I had that <hi>Patience,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That is the Spirits Excellence,</l>
                        <l>That Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n in all his paines did proue,</l>
                        <l>Vnto the Lord to ſhew his Loue:</l>
                        <l>Then ſhould no <hi>Loſſe</hi> of <hi>Lands</hi> or <hi>Goods,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Bring in ſuch Flotes of Sorrowes Floods;</l>
                        <l>Nor <hi>Childrens</hi> Death, nor dogged <hi>Wife,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nor wounded Heart, nor weary Life,</l>
                        <l>Nor Scoffs of Friends, nor words of Griefe,</l>
                        <l>Nor Hearts <hi>Deſpaire</hi> of Hopes Reliefe,</l>
                        <l>Should make me once (which God forbid)</l>
                        <l>Offend his Grace, what ere he did:</l>
                        <l>But ſay with <hi>Iob; If he will kill</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>My heart, yet will I loue him ſtill;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And in his ſight, my Waies reproue,</l>
                        <l>That is the God of gracious Loue.</l>
                        <l>That then, when <hi>All</hi> were at the worſt,</l>
                        <l>And that my Heart were almoſt burſt,</l>
                        <l>My Soule might feele, that Comfort ſweet</l>
                        <l>Did tread all ſorrow vnder Feet.</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Iob</hi> was iuſt, ſo am not I,</l>
                        <l>His God did but his <hi>Patience</hi> try;</l>
                        <l>And made his <hi>Faith</hi> in Mercy, finde</l>
                        <l>The Comfort of a <hi>constant</hi> Minde:</l>
                        <l>But my Soule hath ſo wicked bin,</l>
                        <l>That I am ſcourged for my Sinne,</l>
                        <l>In <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> but with <hi>Mercy</hi> ſuch,</l>
                        <l>As I can neuer praiſe too much.</l>
                        <l>For had not Mercy heal'd my Sore,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18654:11"/>
                        <l>I had bin ſlaine for euermore.</l>
                        <l>But my good GOD is euer <hi>One;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>His Hand is not to <hi>me</hi> alone,</l>
                        <l>But vnto <hi>All</hi> that in diſtreſſe</l>
                        <l>Doe in his Mercy ſeeke redreſſe;</l>
                        <l>And whoſe true <hi>Patience, Faith,</hi> and <hi>Lone,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Doe in his <hi>Iuſtice, Mercy</hi> proue.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="wish">
                     <head>IIII. <hi>Wiſh, or Meditation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OH! that I had that <hi>Gracious Call</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That from the Heauens had bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That choſen Saint of ſacred Bliſſe,</l>
                        <l>Where only Saints true bleſſing is:</l>
                        <l>Who from the way of wicked Thought,</l>
                        <l>Vnto the gates of <hi>Grace</hi> was brought,</l>
                        <l>And when his <hi>Eyes</hi> were ſtricken blinde,</l>
                        <l>Had ſuch an inſight of the <hi>Minde,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>As made him ſee through <hi>Mercies</hi> light,</l>
                        <l>(That is the Soules eternall ſight)</l>
                        <l>How blinde is <hi>Reaſons</hi> ruthfull Eye,</l>
                        <l>Where Errour leads the Heart awry;</l>
                        <l>Whilſt <hi>Conſcience</hi> thinking to doe well,</l>
                        <l>Doth carry <hi>Miſconceit</hi> to Hell;</l>
                        <l>Till <hi>Mercy</hi> meeting on the way.</l>
                        <l>Brings home the Sheepe that went aſtray:</l>
                        <l>Then ſhould no <hi>Office, Power,</hi> nor <hi>Place</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Make me to ſecke my Soules Diſgrace,</l>
                        <l>To take a Tyrants powerfull Rod,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To perſecute the Saints of God.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But I ſhould more in ſoule reioyce</l>
                        <l>In Mercies Gracious-Glorious Choice,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18654:11"/>
                        <l>All <hi>Perſecutions</hi> to abide,</l>
                        <l>Where <hi>Patience, Feith,</hi> and <hi>Loue</hi> is tride</l>
                        <l>Of the ſweet Lord of Heauens Bliſſe,</l>
                        <l>Than perſecute one Saint of his:</l>
                        <l>But all my <hi>Loue,</hi> and Loues <hi>Delight,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>My <hi>Meditation</hi> day and night,</l>
                        <l>Should onely, all, and euer be</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Mercy</hi> that ſo called me.</l>
                        <l>No <hi>Griefe,</hi> no <hi>Paine,</hi> no <hi>Want,</hi> nor <hi>Woe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That I ſhould euer liue to know,</l>
                        <l>But I ſhould thinke too little all,</l>
                        <l>In Loue to anſwer Mercies Call:</l>
                        <l>For all the World I would not care,</l>
                        <l>Nor K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nor <hi>Keſar</hi> would I feare;</l>
                        <l>No <hi>threats,</hi> nor <hi>thraldome, ſcourge</hi> nor <hi>death;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To ſpeake his Praiſe, ſhould ſtop my breath.</l>
                        <l>But I ſhould plainely ſpeake and write</l>
                        <l>My knowledge of the Lord of Light:</l>
                        <l>And to the Glory of his Name,</l>
                        <l>Throughout the World divulge the ſame:</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Walke</hi> ſhould be but in his Wayes;</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Talke</hi> but only in his Praiſe;</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Life</hi> a Death, but in his Loue;</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Death,</hi> a Life, for him to proue:</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Care,</hi> to keepe a Conſcience cleane;</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Will</hi> from wicked thoughts to weane;</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Prayers</hi> for the Good of all,</l>
                        <l>That Mercy vnto Grace doth call:</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Labour,</hi> for the loue of Truth</l>
                        <l>To leade the life of Age and Youth:</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Comfort,</hi> truely to conuert</l>
                        <l>The Soules which Satan did peruert:</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Health,</hi> to labour for their Loue,</l>
                        <l>That ſeeke their bleſſing from aboue.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18654:12"/>
                        <l>My greateſt <hi>Eaſe,</hi> to worke for thoſe</l>
                        <l>Whom Mercy to Saluation choſe:</l>
                        <l>My Paine, and Pleaſure, Trauell, Eaſe,</l>
                        <l>My God <hi>thus</hi> in his Saints to pleaſe.</l>
                        <l>Then ſhould I this <hi>baſe World</hi> deſpiſe,</l>
                        <l>With all Earths <hi>idle Vanities;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And gouerne mine <hi>Affections</hi> ſo,</l>
                        <l>That Sin ſhould neuer ouerthrow</l>
                        <l>This wounded wofull Soule of mine,</l>
                        <l>But ſtill in Mercies loue diuine,</l>
                        <l>My Soule ſhould finde that <hi>life</hi> of Grace,</l>
                        <l>As ſhould all <hi>Earthly loue</hi> deface;</l>
                        <l>And I ſhould onely wiſh to liue,</l>
                        <l>All <hi>Glory</hi> to my God to giue;</l>
                        <l>And all in all my <hi>loy</hi> to bee</l>
                        <l>His <hi>ſeruant</hi> that ſo <hi>called</hi> mee.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="wish">
                     <head>V. <hi>Wiſh, or Meditation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>OH! that my Soule might liue to proue</l>
                        <l>Some part of that ſweet bleſſed Loue,</l>
                        <l>Which IOHN th'Enangeliſt poſſeſt,</l>
                        <l>When he lean'd on our Sunours Breſt;</l>
                        <l>When <hi>Wiſdome, Vertue, Grace</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Embrac'd the bleſſed dayes of <hi>Youth!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Then ſhould I fly with <hi>Eagles</hi> wings</l>
                        <l>Vnto the Glorious King of Kings;</l>
                        <l>And ſee that <hi>Heauenly Court</hi> of his,</l>
                        <l>The Beauty of the Angels Bliſſe;</l>
                        <l>Where <hi>Goodneſſe, Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> dwels,</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Lone,</hi> and <hi>Liſe,</hi> and nothing elſe</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Holineſſe</hi> and Heauenly <hi>Light,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18654:12"/>
                        <l>All, onely in my Sauiours ſight:</l>
                        <l>Then ſhould I <hi>loath</hi> this World of Woe,</l>
                        <l>That doth <hi>bewitch</hi> the Worldling ſo;</l>
                        <l>And ſeeke (but at my Sauiours <hi>feet</hi>)</l>
                        <l>To find my Soules eternall <hi>Sweet;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Till Mercy will vouchſafe me Grace</l>
                        <l>To haue a glimpſe of his ſweet <hi>Face,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>In whoſe leaſt ſweeteſt <hi>Looke</hi> of Loue,</l>
                        <l>A <hi>Sea</hi> of Ioy the <hi>Heart</hi> doth proue;</l>
                        <l>And ſwimming in the Soules Deligh</l>
                        <l>Is <hi>rauiſht</hi> with that Glorious <hi>Sight:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But though I cannot be ſo bleſt,</l>
                        <l>To leane vpon my Sauiours <hi>Breſt;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>As all vnworthy of ſuch Grace,</l>
                        <l>To looke on his Coeleſtiall <hi>Face;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Yet let me beg at <hi>Mercies</hi> Feet,</l>
                        <l>That I may but receiue this Sweet,</l>
                        <l>That when his Saints and Angels ſing</l>
                        <l>Their <hi>Haleluiahs</hi> to their King,</l>
                        <l>My Soule in Ioy all-ſounding then,</l>
                        <l>May haue but leaue to ſing <hi>AMEN.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="elegy">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:13"/>
                  <head>A Funerall PYRAMID</head>
                  <l>TO the deare Memorie of the Moſt deare,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>I conſecrate this Threne, theſe Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Teares:<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Theſe are the Cypreſſe Branches that I beare:</l>
                  <l>The mourning Habit that my ſad Soule weares:</l>
                  <l>This the Impreſa that my Sorrow beares</l>
                  <l>If This not feelingly define my Smart,</l>
                  <l>'Tis not defect of Woe, but Want of skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Art.</l>
                  <l>Within the Center of my trouble Soule,</l>
                  <l>A Monument vnto thy Name Ile build:</l>
                  <l>And there with Teare fil'd Characters inroule</l>
                  <l>Thoſe bright Perfections that thy Life did guild,</l>
                  <l>The Gracefull Good that all thy Actions fil'd: </l>
                  <l>There ſhall my Loue thy ſad Loſſe memorize;</l>
                  <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the World ſhall ceaſe to mind thy Obſequies. </l>
                  <l>Then daigne to take of the obſecureſt hand,</l>
                  <l>Theſe weldeſerued attributes of Praiſe: </l>
                  <l>I know thy Trophies not the higher ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe my hand deſir'd thy Name to raile:</l>
                  <l>Faire Angelized Soule, theſe humble Laies,</l>
                  <l>And worth-leſſe Numbers giue thy light no luſter,</l>
                  <l>But ſhow thoſe ſhapeles Woes that in my Boſom muſter.</l>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ERECTED to the Honor of that rare-vertuous Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman (now in Glory)</hi> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> ELIZABITH GREY, <hi>Daughter to</hi> Richard Grey, <hi>Eſquire, and ſometime Wife to</hi> I. M. <hi>Maſter of Arts.</hi> (BY her Siſter Miſtris <hi>Mary Drayton;</hi> allyed to the Prince of Engliſh Poeſie, MICHAEL DRAYTON, Eſquire) <hi>Interred at</hi> Atherſton: <hi>where ſhe departed this life, calling on the Lord IESVS (to the laſt)</hi> Anno 1614. Ætat. 24.</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Tho. More,</hi> (ſometime L. Chancelor of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) On his owne and his Wiues Tombe:
<q>
                        <l>Ah! ſociet Tumulus, ſociet nos (obſecro) Coelum.</l>
                        <l>Sic Mors non potuit quod dare Vita, dabit.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus rendred:
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O may one Tombe, and Heauen vs re-vnite!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>So Death ſhall riohly my GRBAT LOSSE requite.</hi> I.M.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>MORIERIS, RESVRGES. IVDICABERE.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:13"/>
                  <p>APPENDIX TO PANTHEA.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Plump. Epigram. Ad PONTILIANVM.</bibl>
                     <p>Sunt mala quae culpas (fateor) mala Tempora: ſed tu Temporibus pejor <hi>Pontiliane</hi> malis.</p>
                     <bibl>TIT. 1.13.</bibl>
                     <p>Jncrepa illos dure:</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anno Dionyſiano,</hi> 1630.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:14"/>
                  <head>To the Nobly-deſcended, and Vertuouſly-accompliſht, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> RICHARD GARGRAVE, Knight.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing moued to adioyne to the precedent Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zonets, th'enſuing <hi>Nectarines</hi> of the late Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Viſcount <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>-Albans,</hi> (the Prince of Engliſh Oratory) J preſum'd to inſcribe them <hi>(cum ſuper-pondio)</hi> to your Noble Selfe, whom, for your honorable Quality, rare Skill in Antiquities, exquiſite Iudgement, and generous Loue to Learning, I may iuſtly ſtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>(ſine parpuriſmo)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dulce Camaenarum decus, &amp; Fax aurea Phoebi;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Muſes Darling, and bright <hi>Phoebus</hi> Flame.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>The <hi>Subiect</hi> is ponderous and Diuine, being a graphicall Delineation of Humane Miſery: And well it were with men of Merit, if in this World of Vanity, ſo full of changes and counter-changes, as it ſeems a very <hi>Field of Flint ſowne with Teares;</hi> they were not ouerpreſſed with thoſe <hi>myoparones</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: Vid. Bayſium de Re Nauali.</note> 
                     <hi>piratici,</hi> or Land-pirates, which
<note n="b" place="margin">Orat. in Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marchum.</note> 
                     <hi>Æſchines</hi> ſpeakes of; nor by the combination of prodigious Rakehels, ſurrounded with an <hi>Ocean</hi> of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illany. Such Monſters of Humanity, and Demi-Deuils, are the <hi>Lares et Lemures,</hi> the <hi>Ghoſts</hi> and <hi>Goblins</hi> of this gloomy Age. I remember I haue read in the
<note n="c" place="margin">Digeſted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to 2 Bookes: The 1. <hi>Diabolus infulatus;</hi> or <hi>Plutoes</hi> Peram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>io<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the <hi>North:</hi> Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>pious vſes</hi> of <hi>Guzman d'Alfarache.</hi> The 2. <hi>Diabolus infatuatus,</hi> or, A Spectacle of Bribery and Beggery: Ded. to <hi>Mat. Dodſw.</hi> of <hi>Corke.</hi>
                     </note> Workes of Sir <hi>Io. CRAG,</hi> (a famous Kn. in <hi>Cumberland,</hi>) this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Diſtich;
<q>
                        <l>ONGE walkt the <hi>Vrchin</hi> and the <hi>Elfe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But NOW the <hi>Great Deuill</hi> himſelfe.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the Illuſtration whereof, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>y is pleaſe you to reflect (a little) on the ancient Poets Deſcription of HELL, (the Grand-Deuils HALL) which (they ſay) is <hi>moated round,</hi> and for
<pb facs="tcp:18654:14"/>want of a <hi>BRIDGE, Charon, Plutoes MAN,</hi> ferries ouer <hi>poore Soules</hi> in <hi>white Sheets,</hi> ſometime
<note n="d" place="margin">A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> (at once) in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>an Church, ſeene not long ſince.</note> 
                     <hi>17</hi> at a clap. Vnder which cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Emblem (for it is no vaine Fiction) is mantled a dainty <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,</hi> well knowne to learned <hi>Mythologiſts;</hi> the Reſerch whereof I referre to intelligent Readers ſtudious of <hi>Antique</hi> Matters. Certes, Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> not without cauſe, term'd Poets,
<note n="e" place="margin">See Titus 1.12. and the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Note there.</note> 
                     <hi>Prophets:</hi> for by the Atteſtation of profound <hi>Theologians,</hi> there is (indeed) a Crim-Tartar, <hi>Mogul,</hi> or Captaine-Deuill of that <hi>Tartarean Region,</hi> ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Scripture <hi>Belzebub,</hi> and (miſnamed) by <hi>Exoterick Diuines,
<note n="f" place="margin">Contrary to the iudgement of Antiquity: for in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church diuers were baptized by that Name: as <hi>Lucifer Caralita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> &amp;c.</note> Lucifer:</hi> which <hi>Mille-artifex,</hi> and Maſter-Fiend bath at his becke <hi>Legions</hi> of vnder-miniſters, and (as I may ſay) <hi>Rurall</hi> Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medaries and <hi>Diabolitinoes,</hi> which inceſſantly <hi>ſharke</hi> and ramble abroad for his <hi>Prouant,</hi> (whiles the Great Machiauilian. <hi>Cacus,</hi> or <hi>Cacodaemon</hi> himſelfe ORDINARILY reſides in his <hi>Vulcanian</hi> Forge, and diſmall Den, whetting his griſly-griping Tallons.)</p>
                  <p>But to adjourne the further <hi>Elucidation</hi> hereof to ſome other Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, and to returne to your Honor'd Selfe. If <hi>Criſpinillus Momax</hi> take occaſion hereby (for it is not in my power to ſtop laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Lips) to hiſſe-out his
<q>
                        <l>Bane-ſpitting Murmures, and detracting Spels;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Qualia credibile eſt rictu ructâſſe trifauci</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cerberon, &amp; Stygij Monſtra tremenda Canis:</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I truſt you will (in a ſacred Fury) bandite the ſcandalous <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boune, ad Inſulas fuſtitudinas,</hi> or rather to <hi>Mount-Falcon.</hi> Thus commending th' Addreſse of theſe <hi>Delicatezze</hi> to your Generous Acceptance; whoſe vnparalleld Worth, Noble Esteeme, vndaunted Valour, and Daring (yet Suffering) Spirit (ſuteable to the
<note n="g" place="margin">1. <hi>Gaudet Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia duris.</hi> 2. <hi>Seruire Dea regnare eſt.</hi> 3. <hi>De Gouernour. E. Vent. Grace.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toes</hi> of your Ancient and Renowned Family) deſerue to bee recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to After-Ages; I recommend you to the Higheſt <hi>MAIESTY:</hi> reſting</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Eminent Vertues Votary:
<note n="h" place="margin">
                              <hi>Anagramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmus:</hi> Magua ſumma Artie.</note> BONVS AMICVS ARTI:</hi> Vtriuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Academiae Magiſter.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Humane Life</hi> characterized: By the Right Noble Peere, FRANCIS Viſcount S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Albans,</hi> late L. High Chancelor of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe World's a <hi>Bubble:</hi> and the Life of Man</l>
                     <l>Leſſe then a <hi>Span:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In his <hi>Conception</hi> wretched; from the <hi>Wombe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So to the <hi>Tombe:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Curſt from the <hi>Cradle;</hi> and brought vpto <hi>Yeares,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With <hi>eares</hi> and <hi>feares.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who then to fraile <hi>Mortality</hi> ſhall truſt,</l>
                     <l>But limmes the <hi>Water,</hi> or but writes in <hi>Dust.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet, ſince with Sorrow here we liue oppreſt,</l>
                     <l>What Life is beſt?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Courts</hi> are but only ſuperficiall Schooles</l>
                     <l>To dandle Fooles:</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Rurall parts</hi> are turn'd into a Den</l>
                     <l>Of ſauage Men:</l>
                     <l>And where's a <hi>City</hi> from all Vice ſo free,</l>
                     <l>But may be term'd the worſt of <hi>all the three?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Domeſticke Cares afflict the <hi>Husbands</hi> Bed,</l>
                     <l>Or paines his Head:</l>
                     <l>Thoſe that liue <hi>ſingle,</hi> take it for a Curſe,</l>
                     <l>Or doe things worſe:</l>
                     <l>Some would haue <hi>Children;</hi> thoſe that haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, none;</l>
                     <l>Or wiſh them gone:</l>
                     <l>What is it then to haue, or haue no Wife,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>ſingle Thraldome,</hi> or a <hi>double Strife?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our owne Affections ſtill <hi>at home</hi> to pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>Is a Diſeaſe:</l>
                     <l>To croſſe the Sea to any <hi>forraigne Soile,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Perils and Toile:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18654:15"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Warres</hi> with their noyſe affright vs: when they ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>W'are worſe in <hi>Peace:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What then <hi>remaines?</hi> but that we ſtill ſhould eny,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Not to be borne, or being berne, to dye.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>A ſelect Epigram, written by a Noble Knight <hi>deceaſed: and now inſcribed (as followeth.)</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head>Honoratiſſimae et Nobiliſſ. Ciuitati CESTRIÆ, <hi>Sacrū. Of the Pillars of the Church.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IN old time, <hi>They</hi> were held the Churches Pillars,</l>
                     <l>That did excell in <hi>Learning</hi> and in <hi>Piety,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And were to ALL Examples of Sobriety;</l>
                     <l>Of Chriſts faire Field the true and painfull Tillers:</l>
                     <l>But where are <hi>now</hi> the Men of <hi>that</hi> Society?</l>
                     <l>Are all thoſe Tillers dead? thoſe Pillars broken?</l>
                     <l>No: God forbid ſuch Blaſphemy be ſpoken:</l>
                     <l>I ſay, to ſtop the mouthes of all <hi>ill-willers,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Gods Field hath <hi>Harrowers</hi> ſtill, his Church hath
<note n="*" place="margin">Read P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. c. 28 v. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. and the Geneua Note there. [<hi>Certumeſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> quedam Clereborum, &amp; Crumenimule Demoborum (his) depin,</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Pillers.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> An Elogie and Epitome of the Bible.</head>
                  <salute>To the Right Noble, Religious, &amp; excellent Heroldes; <hi>The Lady Rumney,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Alablaſter; and</hi> Mrs. <hi>Eſther Webbe.</hi>
                  </salute>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THis ſacred Volume, in whoſe precious Leaues</l>
                     <l>The Myſteries of Heauen entreaſur'd lye;</l>
                     <l>Is a cleere Mirror, which no forme deceaues;</l>
                     <l>Th'Obiect and Subiect of each Chriſtian Eye:</l>
                     <l>Who liues <hi>by This,</hi> by Death can neuer dye:</l>
                     <l>Here ſhines the Sun of GRACE, diffuſing wide</l>
                     <l>His quickning Raies on All, from ſide to ſide.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18654:16"/>
                     <l>Here <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> do's Both embrace each other;</l>
                     <l>Met in <hi>one Perſon,</hi> Heauen and Earth do's kiſſe:</l>
                     <l>Here a pure <hi>Virgin</hi> do's become a <hi>Mother,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And bare that SON, who the Worlds Father is,</l>
                     <l>And Maker of his Mother. Here true <hi>Bliſſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Comes flying from the Boſome of the High,</l>
                     <l>And clothes <hi>it ſelfe</hi> in naked Miſery,</l>
                     <l>To drag <hi>Man</hi> out of Hels darke Empery.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Dens ſe Tibi. Tu te Deo.</salute>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="verse_character">
                  <head>CORONIS. A <hi>Character</hi> of the Diuine Graces and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a Vertuous Woman.</head>
                  <salute> To all Noble Ladies, and Gentlewomen of Honor.</salute>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>THat which makes Women beautifull and faire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Is not the</hi> plarting
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>of their</hi> Haire;</l>
                     <l>Iewels <hi>or precious</hi> Stones <hi>ſparkling like Fire;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or putting on of braue</hi> Attire:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But a rich</hi> Tablet <hi>hidden in the Breſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With Heauenly Zeale, like</hi> Rubies <hi>drest:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Amethyſt <hi>of Temperance, enchac't</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In Flowers of Gold, with</hi> Saphire <hi>chaſt:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Th'abſequious</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Plin. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 37. <hi>cap.</hi> 30.</note> Helintrope, <hi>wilde</hi> Iaſper <hi>ſtone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> Opal <hi>of all Worthe in One:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pure</hi> Cryſtall, <hi>glittering with immortall Light,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shewing a rare-ſweet-Chriſtian Spright:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Lilly-Robe <hi>of Innocence put on,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Richer then that of</hi> Salomon.</l>
                     <l>Thus <hi>deckt, you rauiſh</hi> Angels <hi>with your Lones,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This <hi>is the Beauty GOD approues.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18654:16"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
